# PAULO BRUNO SERAFIM

## XAI Researcher | PhD Student @ GSSI

I like to solve challenging problems using my creativity, developing new solutions to relevant and nontrivial assignments. Throughout my experience on different academic projects, I became a person who not only loves resolving problems through innovation but also enjoys writing about them.

### **SKILLS**

**C/C++** 9 years

Data-Oriented and Object-Oriented C/C++

**Python** 7 years

Numpy, Scikit, Pandas, Matplotlib

Julia 2 years

WorldDynamics.jl, Flux.jl, ModelingToolkit.jl

**Assembly** 1 year

Z80 processor (GBASM)

**Reinforcement Learning** 7 years

Deep Q-Networks and Policy Gradients

**Explainable AI** 3 years

OmniXAI, XRL, Natural Language Explanations

Large Language Models 1 year

GPT-3.5, GPT-4, Guidance

### **LANGUAGES**

PT Native Speaker

**EN** Full Professional Proficiency

Professional Working Proficiency

FR Elementary Proficiency

#### SOCIAL

paulobruno.github.io

in linkedin.com/in/pbserafim

github.com/paulobruno

iD orcid.org/0000-0002-5980-8149

#### CONTACT

L'Aquila, AQ, Italy

+39 0862 4280 262

paulo.desousa@gssi.it

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### **Research Engineer**

Apr. 2022 - Oct. 2022

INRIA Sophia Antipolis

Implemented a novel Locality-Sensitive Hashing algorithm developed in the group, performed benchmarks, and wrote reports of experiments on Machine Learning datasets. Started development of an internal package for Neural Network pruning. Lead programmer of WorldDynamics.jl, an open-source framework for world dynamics modeling and simulation written in Julia.

#### **Senior Data Scientist**

May 2021 - Mar. 2022

Instituto Atlântico

Tech Lead of the Data Science branch of an R&D project for Dell EMC. Working with anomaly detection using unsupervised learning methods, classification using supervised learning methods, and development of Business Intelligence dashboards to assist tactical and operational decision-making. Responsible for writing and presenting technical reports to Dell EMC managers.

### **Computer Vision Engineer**

Sep. 2020 - Apr. 2021

Instituto Atlântico

Worked on an R&D Computer Vision project for HP Inc. applying Deep Learning to the problems of human segmentation and image matting using TensorFlow. Worked on OCR methods applied to printed text documents. Developed a synthetic document generator using OpenCV. Co-leader of the Cognitive Computing study group, focused on CV, Image Processing, and Reinforcement Learning.

## Computer Graphics Engineer Feb. 2019 - Aug. 2020

Instituto Atlântico

Worked on R&D projects for HP Labs on 3D printing, applying computer graphics methods using only C/C++ standard libraries. Developed a new way to build voxelized tree-like support structures, which generated a patent application (2019). Worked on improvements of Genetic Algorithm heuristics applied to a Bin Packing Problem (2020).

#### **Software Developer**

May 2018 - Feb. 2019

GREat - ASTEF

Developed solutions for fingerprint minutiae extraction and matching focused on high performance, using OpenCV in C++. Implemented a data-oriented C++ version of SourceAFIS, reducing runtime in about 90%. Created a side project using Convolutional Neural Networks for fingerprint Region of Interest (ROI) segmentation. Worked on a Transfer Learning solution to enhance fingerprint images. Helped the team with singular point detection using YOLOv4.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### PhD - Computer Science

Nov. 2022 - Present

Gran Sasso Science Institute (GSSI)

Advisor: Pierluigi Crescenzi Co-Advisor: Fosca Giannotti

Research on Conversational Explainable AI (XAI) through the use

of Large Language Models.

## MSc - Computer Science Mar. 2016 - Apr. 2018

Federal University of Ceara (UFC)

Advisor: Dr. Joaquim Bento Cavalcante Neto Co-Advisors: Dr. Creto Vidal and Dr. Yuri Nogueira

Thesis: Evaluating competition in training of Deep Reinforcement Learning agents in First-Person Shooter games (in Portuguese)

Research on multi-agent competitive applications of Deep Q-Networks using the environment ViZDoom and TensorFlow.

## BSc - Computer Science Jan. 2013 - Dec. 2015

Federal University of Ceara (UFC)

Magna Cum Laude degree

Worked on hair animation projects using mass-spring systems and OpenGL (2013). Developed research on Neuroevolution for autonomous game agents (2014-2015).

#### PERSONAL RESEARCH

## Deep RL Researcher

Apr. 2018 - Present

CRAb - Computer Graphics, Virtual Reality and Animation

Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) researcher, working with autonomous game agents using TensorFlow and PyTorch, and the environments ViZDoom, OpenAl Gym, and Unity ML-Agents. Co-advisor of one BSc, two MSc, and one PhD candidate students. Currently working on analysis of agent's performance under different views of the same scenario by using model interpretability methods.

#### **STUDENTS**

Halisson Rodrigo	PhD	2020-Present
Alexandre Magno	BSc/MSc	2019-Present
Rômulo Férrer Filho	BSc/MSc	2019-Present
Hyuan Farrapo	BSc	2020-2022
Anderson Oliveira	BSc/MSc	2017-2020
Matheus Cordeiro	BSc	2017-2019
Eduardo Melo	BSc	2015-2017
Gabriel Costa	BSc	2015-2017

## **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS**

WorldDynamics.jl: A Julia Package for Developing and Simulating Integrated Assessment Models

Mar. 2024

Journal of Open Source Software

Pierluigi Crescenzi, Emanuele Natale, Aurora Rossi, Paulo B. Serafim.

Assessing the Robustness of Deep Q-Network Agents to Changes on Game Object Textures

Oct. 2021

XX Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames)

Paulo B. S. Serafim, Yuri L. B. Nogueira, Creto A. Vidal, Joaquim B. Cavalcante-Neto.

Deep Reinforcement Learning em Ambientes Virtuais (in Portuguese)

Nov. 2020

Book Chapter in Introduction to Virtual and Augmented Reality

Paulo B. S. Serafim, Yuri L. B. Nogueira, Joaquim B. Cavalcante-Neto, Creto A. Vidal.

Generating Supports Nov. 2019

Patent WO2021107916A1

Jun Zeng, Paulo Bruno Serafim, Alyne Gomes Soares Cantal

## **REFERENCES**

#### Dr. Pierluigi Crescenzi

PhD Advisor
Full Professor
Gran Sasso Science Institute
orcid.org/0000-0001-8789-3195
pierluigi.crescenzi@gssi.it

#### Dr. Emanuele Natale

Employer and Research Supervisor CNRS Researcher Université Côte d'Azur, INRIA, I3S orcid.org/0000-0002-8755-3892 emanuele.natale@inria.fr

#### Dr. Joaquim Cavalcante Neto

MSc and BSc Advisor
Full Professor
Federal University of Ceara
orcid.org/0000-0003-1143-6662
joaquimb@dc.ufc.br